Cecil Jensen Papers
Cecil Jensen Papers
1865-1971
1940-1971
Jensen, Cecil, 1902-1976
11 linear ft.
Over 1200 original editorial cartoons drawn for the Chicago Daily News, correspondence, clippings of editorial cartoons and printed material including an item produced by the Sam Adams Committee of Public Safety
149083
Biographical History
Cecil Jensen (1902-1976) was an American editorial cartoonist.
Jensen was born in Ogden, Utah on January 17, 1902. After high school, Jensen studied at the Chicago Academy of Fine Arts. Jensen moved to California and worked his way into editorial cartooning at the Los Angeles Illustrated Daily News. In 1928, Jensen returned to Chicago as editorial cartoonist for the Chicago Daily News where he spent the remainder of his career. Sigma Delta Chi recognized Jensen's work with an award in 1953.
Jensen also drew comic strips. During World War II, he caricatured Chicago Tribune publisher Colonel McCormick in Colonel McCosmic. Beginning in 1946 Jensen drew Elmo and Debbie (later transformed by the Register and Tribune Syndicate into Debbie or Little Debbie as it was commonly known).
Cecil Jensen died in May 1976.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Cecil Jensen Papers are divided into three series.
Cartoons contains more than 1,200 original editorial cartoons drawn by Jensen for the Chicago Daily News. The cartoons are undated and arranged alphabetically by caption. (Cartoons do have months and days of the week listed, but lack years). Based on subject matter, the majority were likely drawn in the 1960s with some from the 1940s and the 1970s. Subject matter includes national and international politics as well as local issues related to the Chicago area.
Individual cartoons measure approximately 14 ½" x 16 ½" with some variations of about 1". Jensen worked in ink and crayon on illustration board; traces of pencil are visible. Captions and limited date information appear in pencil.
Correspondence (1961-1967) is comprised of incoming correspondence. Letters include requests and thank you notes for original cartoons as well as reprint permissions and feedback from readers. Included are letters from elected officials including Robert F. Kennedy (2 letters), Donald Rumsfeld and Charles Percy. Worth noting is the folder from Illinois State Senator Hudson R. Sours which contains several nineteenth century documents: a promissary note; 1865 document for property in Eureka, Illinois; and a 1869 mortgage for property in New York City near 3rd Avenue and 56th Street. Also of interest are enclosures related to the right to work law (14B of the Taft-Hartley Act).
Other letters were written by fellow cartoonists including Newton Pratt, Art Wood, Arthur Poinier, Bill Saunders, Eldon Pletcher and Mrs. Carey Orr Cook. Correspondence from Poinier includes the results of a survey conducted by the Association of American Editorial Cartoonists of journalism schools and curriculum related to editorial cartooning.
The Printed Material (1938-1967) series includes clippings and miscellaneous material. The bulk of this series is clippings of Jensen's editorial cartoons with information about the date of publication. Also located in the series are clippings of work by other editorial cartoonists, namely John Fischetti, Dan Dowling and Arthur Poinier. Finally, of particular interest is a publication from the Sam Adams Committee of Public Safety. The booklet contains editorial cartoons (including work by Jensen) that have been altered to express white supremacist messages.
Arrangement of the Collection
Original artwork is arranged in alphabetical order by caption. Correspondence is arranged in alphabetical order by sender's last name. Clippings are arranged by year.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
The Cartoonist and... Your Right to Work, a booklet by National Right to Work Committee has been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Jensen, Cecil, 1902-1976.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Sam Adams Committee of Public Safety.; United Nations -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Goldwater, Barry M. (Barry Morris), 1909-1998 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Khrushchev, Nikita Sergeevich, 1894-1971 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Daley, Richard J., 1902-1976 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ) -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Chicago Daily News, Inc.; Democratic Party (U.S.) -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States. -- Congress. -- Caricatures and cartoons.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- Chicago (Ill.); Cartoonists -- United States.; Civil rights movements -- United States -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cold War -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Communism -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Crime -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Editorial cartoons -- Chicago (Ill.); Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Elections -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Nuclear weapons -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Racism -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Taxation -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; White supremacy movements -- Caricatures and cartoons.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Correspondence.; Editorial cartoons.; Clippings (information artifacts); Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Majority, gift of Cecil Jensen, 1964-1965, 1967-1968, 1972
Two cartoons ("You're just not built right to be a patriot" and "Termites"), gift of Joseph E. Geshwiler, 2008.
Seven World War II-related cartoons ("Anybody who deserts us is nuts," "Atlas", "The fugitive," "The gift horse," Holding that line," In democracy's corner," and "That's the trouble with cats"), gift of Arthur Vyse, 2014.
Inventory
- Cartoons
  - A-B, 118 items (Oversize 1)
  - C-Far, 127 items (Oversize 2)
  - Fas-He, 144 items (Oversize 3)
  - Hi-It, 142 items (Oversize 4)
  - Iv-Mak, 82 items (Oversize 5)
  - Ma-Not, 82 items (Oversize 6)
  - Not-Pau, 127 items (Oversize 7)
  - Po-S, 136 items (Oversize 8)
  - T, 117 items (Oversize 9)
  - U-Win, 113 items (Oversize 10)
  - Wit-Y, 56 items (Oversize 11)
- Correspondence
  - A-B, 1964; 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - C-E, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - F-K, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Kennedy, Robert F., 1961 (Box 1)
  - L-R, 1964-1967 (Box 1)
  - Rumsfeld, Donald, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Sours, Hudson R., 1865; 1869,; 1967 (Box 1)
  - S-Z, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, 1965-1966; undated (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Clippings, editorial cartoons by Jensen and other cartoonists
    - 1938-1941, 1943 (Box 1)
    - 1944-1946, 1952-1954 (Box 2)
    - 1954-1957 (Box 3)
    - 1958-1960, 1962 (Box 4)
    - 1962, 1964-1965 (Box 5)
  - Sam Adams Committee of Public Safety, 1960s; booklet of cartoons altered to reflect white supremacist views (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1964-1965; 1967; clippings, receipts, proofs (Box 1)
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may require you to browse with alternative terms.
B= Box, For example: B1= Box 1
Adenauer, Konrad B1 B4 B9
AFL-CIO B6 B10
Africa B9-B10
Agnew, Spiro T. B6 B8
Agricultural Adjustment Administration B1
airline industry B9-B10
Alabama B2 B8
Albania B3
Algeria B1 B3 B7 B10
Ali, Muhammad B1 B5
aliens B11
aluminum industry B4
American Indians B9
American Medical Association B2 B11
Arkansas B7
armed forces B1-B4 B7-B10
Asia B1 B9-B11
auto industry B5-B9
automation B1 B6 B8-B9
Baker, Bobby B2 B4-B6 B8-B11
Ben Bella, Ahmed B2
Berlin B1 B4-B6 B9-B11
Berlin Wall B6 B8-B10
big business B1 B3-B4 B6 B10
Black Power B1
boycotts B5 B10
Brazil B3 B8
Brezhnev, Leonid Ilyich B11
Britain B2-B7 B9-B10
Buddhists B10
budget B1 B3-B5 B7-B8
Burch, Dean B8
Byrd, Harry B7
California B3 B7
Canada B1 B3 B8
capitalism B9-B10
Carpenter, Scott B3
Castro, Fidel B1-B5 B7-B10
Central Intelligence Agency B1-B2 B7 B8 B10
Chicago B1-B11
Chicago Seven B7
China B1-B11
civil defense B2-B3 B8
civil liberties B7
civil rights B2-B5 B7-B11
Cold War B1 B3-B4 B7-B8 B10
college students B2
colonialism B1
communism B1-B3 B5-B11
Congo B3 B7
Congress B1 B3-B11
Congress of Racial Equality B8-B10
Connally, John B7
consumers B1 B7 B9
corruption B2 B6 B8
cost of living B3-B4 B7 B11
credit B7 B8
crime B1-B8 B9-B11
criminals B2-B3 B8
Cuba B1-B10
Cyprus B5-B6
Daley, Richard J. B1-B3 B7-B9
de Gaulle, Charles B1-B5 B7-B11
debt B1 B9-B10
democracy B1
Democratic Party B1-B11
Diefenbaker, John B4 B8
Diem, Ngo Dinh B3 B11
Dirksen, Everett B2 B9
disarmament B1 B3-B4 B7-B9
Dodd, Thomas J. B9
Dominican Republic B3-B4 B7-B9
Douglas, William O. B2-B3 B8
draft B3-B6 B11
driving B1 B5-B6 B8-B9
Duvalier, François B6
economy B1-B11
education B1-B8 B10-B11
Egypt B1 B4 B9 B11
Eisenhower, Dwight B2 B3 B4
elections B1 B3 B5-B10
En-lai, Chou B3
espionage B8
ethics B2-B4 B6 B10
Europe B1-B5 B7-B8 B11
farming B1-B3 B7-B9 B11
Faubus, Orval B7
federal aid B1 B7 B11
Federal Bureau of Investigation B6
Federal Communications Commission B2
Federal Reserve B4
Field, Marshall B1
Florida B4 B8 B10
food B6 B7 B9
Ford, Gerald R. B2
foreign aid bill B1-B2 B5 B8-B9
foreign policy B2-B4 B6 B8-B11
France B1 B3 B5 B7-B11
free press B2-B3 B10
Free Society Association B7
freedom B5 B9 B11
freedom of information B10-B11
Freeman, Orville B11
Fulbright, J. William B1 B6
gambling B4
Geneva B4 B8-B9
Georgia B5 B6
Germany B1-B2 B4 B9 B11
Giancana, Sam B8-B9
Glenn, John B3 B6
Glimco, Joseph B9
gold prices B10
Goldwater, Barry B1-B10
government spending B1-B4 B7-B11
Great Depression B4
Great Society B5 B7-B9 B11
Greece B3 B6
Gromyko, Andrei B6-B7 B9
Guantanamo B2 B7
Guinea B8
gun control B3 B7
Haiti B6 B10
healthcare B1-B2 B4-B5 B8
Hess, Rudolf B3
highway construction B4 B7 B9
Ho Chi Minh B1 B3-B5 B6 B9
Hoffa, Jimmy B3 B5-B8 B10
holidays B2 B4 B6 B9-B11
Honduras B9
Hoover, Hebert B2
housing B2 B4 B6-B7 B10
Humphrey, Hubert B4 B8-B9
Illinois B1-B11
India B2 B6-B9
India-Pakistan War B1-B2 B4 B7 B9
Indonesia B2-B4 B6 B9
industry (general) B1 B8
inflation B2-B4 B6-B10
insurance B4-B5
integration B4 B8
Internal Revenue Service B4 B9
Interstate Commerce Commission B7
Israel B1 B3-B4 B9
Italy B7
Japan B2 B10
jobs B2 B5-B6 B8-B11
John Birch Society B8
Johnson, Lady Bird B4
Johnson, Lyndon Baines B1-B11
Jordan B4
journalism B2 B10
judicial system B5
justice B7-B8 B10
Kefauver, Estes B1-B2 B4 B7-B8
Kennedy, Caroline B8 B10
Kennedy, Jacqueline B8
Kennedy, John F. B1 B3-B11
Kennedy, Robert F. B1-B2 B4-B9
Kennedy, Ted B8 B10
Kentucky B3
Kerner Jr., Otto B2 B8-B9 B11
Khrushchev, Nikita B1-B11
King Jr., Martin Luther B2
Korea B2 B7 B8
Kosygin, Alexey B3 B9
Ku Klux Klan B4 B9-B10
Ky, Nguyen Cao B1 B5 B9
labor B1-B2 B4-B11
Labor Day B3
Laos B1 B3 B5 B11
Latin America B1 B4-B5 B10-B11
law and order B1 B4-B5 B8-B11
Lindsay, John B10
living conditions B2
Lodge, George C. B10
Lodge Jr., Henry Cabot B3 B8
MacMillan, Harold B2 B7 B9
Makarios III B5
Malaysia B9
Manila Summit Conference B2-B3 B6
Mantle, Mickey B5
Massachusetts B7 B10
Malaysia B2
McNamara, Robert B2 B6-B8
Meany, George B3
Medicare B2-B5 B7-B9 B11
Mexico B7
Michigan B1-B2 B4 B9 B11
Middle East B3-B4 B6-B7 B9
Mikoyan, Anastas B4
Miller, Arthur B8
Miller, William E. B8
minimum wage B1
Mississippi B2-B3 B10
Nasser, Gamal Abdel B1 B3 B6-B11
National Collegiate Athletic Association B10
nationalism B1 B8
NATO B1 B3 B5-B6 B10
nature conservation B1-B2 B4 B7-B8
Nazi GermanyB1 B3 B4 B9
Nehru, Jawaharlal B1 B7
Netherlands B6
neutrality B7 B8 B11
New Deal B9
New Hampshire B5-B6
New York B1-B2 B4-B5 B7-B8 B10
New York City B1-B2 B8
Nhu, Madame Ngo Dinh B8-B9 B11
Nixon, Richard M. B1-B4 B6-B10
Nkhrumah, Kwame B8
nuclear weapons B1-B5 B7-B11
O'Brien, Larry B6
oil B9
Organization of American States B1 B3 B7 B10
organized crime B4 B6 B8-B11
Pakistan B2
Panama B8
patriotism B2
peace B1-B3 B4-B10
Pearson, Lester B. B4
Pentagon B6 B9
Percy, Charles H. B2-B3 B9
Philippines B1
police B4-B5 B7 B9-B10
politicians B3 B8-B9
politics B10
pollution B1-B2 B4
population B2
poverty B2 B4 B6-B7 B9-B10
Powell Jr., Adam Clayton B1 B3-B5 B7-B10
Powell, Stanley M. B9
prices B2-B3 B5-B9
prisoners of war B1 B7 B9-B10
Profumo, John B2 B4
prosperity B1 B6-B11
public opinion B1-B6 B8-B10
Puerto Rico B9
race relations B1-B2 B10
racism B1-B2 B4-B6 B9
railroad industry B2-B10
recession B8-B9
religion B7
Republican Party B1-B10
Reuther, Walter B3
riots B1-B2
Rockefeller, David B4
Rockefeller, Nelson B1 B4 B6-B7 B10
Romania B3
Romney, George W. B1
Rusk, Dean B2 B8
Russia B1-B2 B5 B7 B9-B10
school dropouts B6
schools B4 B7-B11
science B3 B9
Scranton, William B2-B3 B6-B9
segregation B1
Singapore B2
social security B2-B3 B8-B9
socialized medicine B2 B8
soil and water management B2
South America B7
Soviet Union B1-B11
space exploration B1-B3 B6-B10
sports B1-B3 B5-B6 B8-B11
Stalin, Joseph B6
Stassen, Harold B2
steel industry B1-B2 B4-B5 B7 B9-B11
Stevenson, Adlai E. B4
stock market B1-B4 B6-B8 B10
strikes B1 B3 B5 B7-B10
Sukarno B2-B4 B6 B8 B11
Supreme Court B4
Syria B4
tariffs B1-B3 B6-B7
taxes B1-B11
Taylor, Maxwell B3
teachers B4 B8
Teamsters B7-B9
television B5 B9
terrorism B1
Texas B9
Thailand B7
Thieu, Nguyen Van B1
Thurmond, Strom B2
Tito, Josip Broz B2 B8-B9
Toure, Ahmed Sekou B8
tourism B1
trade B1-B3 B6-B8
transit and transportation B6-B8 B10
Tshombe, Moise B7
Turkey B6
U.S. Dollar B5 B10
U.S. Senate B1-B5 B8-B10
Ulbricht, Walter B4 B10-B11
unemployment B1 B3-B4 B8-B9
unions B3 B5-B11
United Auto Workers B6
United Nations B1 B3-B11
urban problems B10
urban renewal B4 B7-B9
Venezuela B3
Vietnam B1-B11
Vietnam War B1-B7 B9-B10
voting B1-B3 B5-B11
voting rights B7 B10
wage and price controls B3-B4 B7-B9
Wallace, George B1 B3-B5 B7-B8 B10
war B1 B4 B8-B11
War on Poverty B1-B5 B7-B9
water safety B2
weapons B2-B3 B8-B9
weather B3-B5 B9-B11
Weaver, Robert C. B9
welfare B3 B6-B7 B10
white supremacy B1 B4-B5 B10
White, Byron B2
Wilson, Harold B1-B3
Yugoslavia B9
Zedong, Mao B1-B3 B6-B11